本期视频由Wix赞助，字幕翻译给虫
This video was made possible by Wix.
前往下方链接让原视频作者恰饭
Build your website easily at wix.com/go/wendover.
这是波音737 MAX——一款全新的飞机……算是吧
This is a 737 MAX—a brand new airplane… almost.
它有几个与众不同的特点
It has a few aspects that makes it unique.
绝大多数现代飞机都有电子检查单
Most modern airplane have electronic pre-flight checklists.
737 MAX还在用纸质的
The 737 MAX uses paper checklists.
绝大多数现代飞机启动只需要拨一个开关
Most modern airplanes can be turned on by flipping a switch.
737 MAX的启动程序却有7步
The 737 MAX uses a seven step process.
绝大多数现代飞机有电子显示屏显示确切的报警信息
Most modern airplanes have electronic on-screen warnings describing exactly what a problem is.
737 MAX却只有警告灯
The 737 MAX only has a warning light.
绝大多数现代飞机是全电传操控的
Most modern airplanes are fully fly-by-wire
它们的副翼、升降舵等操控面都是由电子信号控制伺服电机驱动的
meaning their ailerons and elevators and other flight control surfaces move by electronic signals triggering servo motors.
737 MAX却用驾驶舱伸出的钢索拉动绝大多数操控面
The 737 MAX has, running from the cockpit, physical cables themselves pulling most of the flight control surfaces to move.
这些设计并不都是坏的过时的
Not all of these design elements are necessarily bad things
——比如实际上很多飞行员更喜欢钢索的机械操控
—many pilots, in fact, prefer the fly-by-cable system, for example
——但737 MAX和其它现代飞机还有一个最大的不同
—but there is one other big difference between most modern airplanes and the 737 MAX.
绝大多数现代飞机在天上飞呢，但737 MAX都在地上停着呢
Most modern airplanes are flying up above right now, the 737 MAX is not.
这些设计元素个个都有737 MAX祖先的基因在里面
These design elements are all indicators of a truth about the 737 MAX
——这是一架有着五十年历史的飞机
—it’s a 50 year old airplane
经过了改装、换发动机与三次重新设计才成就了其今日的模样
retooled, re-engined, and redesigned three times to make it what it is today.
它是今天仍在制造的最古老的主流商用机型
It is the oldest major commercial plane-type still being made today and it shows.
737 MAX上大部分设计的设计者可能都已经去世
Much of of the design of the 737 MAX was done by people not even alive today.
波音一遍一遍改造这架飞机的原因
The reason Boeing revamped and revamped and revamped this airplane over and over and over again
与整个航空工业的经济有关，也与世界上最激烈的竞争之一有关
has to do with the economics of the aviation industry as a whole and of one of the world’s fiercest rivalries
——这两家就是波音和空客
—Boeing versus Airbus.
早在2011年，就有传言说波音要设计一款全新单通道飞机取代737
Back in 2011, rumblings were emerging that Boeing would design an all-new single-aisle airplane to replace the rather old 737.
这似乎是更合理的选择，可以让制造商设计出更有效率的飞机
It seemed like the logical choice that would allow the manufacturer to design a far more efficient aircraft
而不必受737机型的旧的金属机身、技术的限制
unconstrained by the 737’s old, metallic airframe and technologies.
但波音之所以可能不会选择过早放弃737
The reason Boeing might not have chosen to scrap the 737 earlier, though,
是因为航空公司并不那么看重短途飞机的燃油效率
is because, to airlines, fuel efficiency matters less for their short-haul planes.
这部分原因单纯是因为小飞机每天飞行时间较短
That’s partially just because smaller planes fly fewer hours per day.
比如在美国航空公司中，窄体飞机每天平均飞行8.2小时
Among American airlines, for example, the average small narrow-body plane spends 8.2 hours airborne per day
而宽体飞机每天要飞11.5小时
while the average wide-body plane spends 11.5 hours airborne.
但同时，窄体飞机每天平均飞行4.5班次
Meanwhile, though, the average small, narrow-body plane flies 4.5 flights per day
而宽体飞机平均每天只飞1.5班次
whereas the average wide-body flies just 1.5 per day.
小型飞机飞的航线短，所以它们会花费更长的时间在地面上装货卸货
Considering small planes fly shorter routes, they spend more time on the ground unloading and loading between flights.
所以，更短的飞行时间让在燃油的花费上
So, with fewer hours per day in the air, the proportion of cost devoted to fuel
小飞机比大飞机更少
is lower to operate small planes than big planes.
传统地讲，航司宁愿买便宜的小飞机，而不是昂贵的高效率的小飞机
Traditionally, airlines would rather have a cheap, small plane rather than an expensive, super efficient small plane.
737就是又小又便宜的飞机
The 737 is just that—it’s a cheap, small plane.
737-700的标价只有8900万美元，实际成交价会比这更低
The 737-700’s list price is only $89 million and, once airlines actually negotiate an order, the real price is far less.
凭借半个多世纪的经验，波音的737制造工艺已经相当完善
With over 50 years of experience, Boeing has perfected the 737 manufacturing process and
因此能够以很低的价格交付飞机
is therefore able to offer the plane at a relatively cheap price.
波音最快的时候平均14小时就能造一架737
At their peak, Boeing was making one 737 every 14 hours.
所以总的来说，当航司考虑优先买哪种飞机的时候
So, in summary, when prioritizing which planes to buy,
他们会青睐升级远程宽体飞机为最新、最省油的机型，而不是小飞机
airlines are going to be more focused on upgrading their long-haul, wide-body fleets to the newest, most fuel-efficient airplanes
than their small planes.
但过去十来年，航空公司运营窄体飞机的策略有所改变
In the past decade or so, though, airlines have been changing how they’ve been using narrow-body planes.
像737、A320、757这些航司短途航线主力机型
Planes like the 737, A320, and 757 have long been the core of almost any airlines’ short-haul fleet
开始执行越来越长的航线了
but they’ve started to be used for longer and longer flights.
这些小飞机运营成本低，又有了更长航程的新设计
These smaller planes are cheaper to operate and have been getting redesigned with longer and longer range
让航司能运营宽体飞机装不满的小需求、远程的航线
which allow airlines to operate longer routes with less demand that couldn’t fill a larger, wide-body plane.
美国航空公司的机队机龄就能恰好说明这一点
The fleet age of United’s planes, for example, indicates just this.
你会发现其大部分窄体飞机是90年代或者本世纪初的
You can see that the average age of most of their narrow-body fleet is from the late 1990’s and early 2000’s
但其多数宽体飞机都是最近十年才服役的
while much of their wide-body fleet was put into service in the current decade.
而至于变化，你可以发现窄体飞机在过去20年内
But going back to what’s changed, you can see that with small, narrow-body planes, over the past twenty years,
平均每日飞行班次越来越少，平均每日飞行时间越来越长
these planes are flying fewer and fewer flights per day while being airborne for more and more hours per day
说明它们飞的航线越来越远了
meaning they’re flying longer and longer routes.
另外在2011年，当波音在决定737计划之后的安排时
In addition, in 2011, when Boeing was deciding what to do next with the 737 program,
航空燃油价格已接近历史最高水平
jet fuel prices had reached close to an all-time high
所以即使是对于小飞机，航司也会更加关注燃油效率
so airlines were more concerned than ever about fuel efficiency, even for their smaller planes.
所以这些小型窄体飞机的燃油效率变得越来越重要
Therefore, the fuel efficiency of these small, narrow-body planes was and is becoming more and more important.
这就是除了对提高燃油效率的呼声很高之外
That, in addition to a general need to improve efficiency over time,
波音想要设计全新窄体飞机的原因
was why Boeing was looking to create an all new narrow-body airplane.
但也要考虑历史的进程
But then reality hit.
在2010年12月1日，空客宣布了更换发动机后
On December 1, 2010, Airbus announced that it would release a re-engined,
320系列更高效率的版本——A320Neo
more efficient version of their A320 family aircraft—the A320Neo.
对于波音来说很不幸，A320Neo前几个月卖的太好了
Unfortunately for Boeing, the A320Neo sold quite well in its first few months.
很明显，航司青睐更快、更高效的小飞机
It was clear that airlines wanted a more efficient small plane, and fast.
又没过多久，更糟的事情来了
Soon after, something worse happened.
当时世界上最大的航司之一美国航空公司在2011年是没有空客的
American airlines, which was, at the time, one of the world’s largest airlines, had no Airbus planes in 2011.
他们所有的远程飞机和大多数短途飞机都是波音制造的
All of their long haul fleet and most of their short-haul fleet was built by Boeing.
但在2011年7月20日，美航宣布了一笔460架窄体飞机的大订单
On July 20, 2011, though, American announced a massive order for 460 narrow-body planes
——130架A320，130架A320Neo，100架737，100架“新发动机737”
—130 Airbus A320s, 130 Airbus A320Neos, 100 737s, and 100 re-engined 737s.
公告中说，美航“意向订购100架波音全新版本的737NG飞机
The press release said, American, “intends to order 100 of Boeing's expected new evolution of the 737NG,
其配备新发动机，有比现型号更高的燃油效率”
with a new engine that would offer even more significant fuel-efficiency gains over today's models.”
在当时，这款“新发动机737”还未公布
At this point, this re-engined 737 had not been announced.
美航给一款不存在的飞机下了订单
American announced an order for a non-existent plane.
他们“强迫”波音给737换新发动机，而不是让他们研发全新机型
They strong-armed Boeing into re-engining their 737 rather than building a new airplane
美航的手段就是给他们下这笔“想象中的飞机”的订单
by dangling an order of this hypothetical revamped airplane over them.
波音也很有可能早已内定了“换发动机”的方案
It’s likely that Boeing had already agreed internally to re-engine the plane
但不说别的，就说美国航空公司这样做目的何在？
but nonetheless, why would American do that?
他们为何非要买效率不高、现代化程度不高的“新发动机737”
Why would they want a less efficient, less modern re-engined 737 over a more modern,
却不想要全新研发的更高效的窄体客机呢？
more efficient brand new narrow-body plane?
简言之，油钱相比总开销，微不足道
Well, in short, it’s because fuel cost is far from all the cost.
飞行员通常是只为一种机型而训练的
Pilots are generally trained to operate just one type of aircraft.
有些人飞A380，有些人飞777，有些飞A320，有些飞737
Some fly the A380, some fly the 777, some fly the A320, and some fly the 737
但飞行员不会只飞737-700、或-800，或-900，而是飞整个737系列
but they don’t fly the 737-700 or 737-800 or 737-900, they fly the 737 airplane as a whole.
飞行员训练飞某种系列机型，而不是某个非常具体的型号
Pilots are trained to the aircraft, not the specific aircraft variant.
一般来说，飞行员可以随时在一个系列的机型中随意更换
In general, pilots can and do switch between variants of aircraft even in any given day
在更换系列内几款衍生型号时不需要额外训练
and are not required to do any substantial training to be certified on different aircraft variants.
更重要的是，FAA并不要求飞行员飞新737之前必须完成模拟机训练
Crucially, the FAA has never required that 737 pilots complete any simulator training before flying new 737 variants.
因为50岁的737飞起来和1岁的新款737差别不大
That’s because a 50 year-old 737 more or less flies like a 1 year-old 737.
美航想要新款737而不是全新的机型
American wanted a refreshed 737 over a new plane
是因为他们已经有上千名经过训练、认证的737飞行员了
since they already had thousands of trained and certified 737 pilots.
他们不可能有飞行员会飞波音全新研发的飞机
They had no pilots for a hypothetical new narrow-body Boeing
而将来训练飞行员驾驶新飞机的成本将是巨大的
and the cost of training their pilots to a new plane would be massive.
即使你不管训练成本
Even ignoring the training costs, though,
航司运营同一型号机队的成本也比运营不同型号的低很多
it’s far cheaper for airlines to just have one large fleet of one type of aircraft
rather than a few smaller fleets of different aircraft.
这也是为何像瑞安、易捷、西南航空这种廉航通常只运营一种机型
That’s why budget airlines like Ryanair, EasyJet, and Southwest each operate only one aircraft type.
只需一组飞行员和技师就能运营所有的飞机，成本很低
It costs less to just have one group of pilots and mechanics that can work on all the planes
这就是为什么航司都想尽可能拥有更少种类的机型
and that’s why most airlines try to have as few different aircraft types as possible.
所以，在美航的订单公布不久，波音官方就公开了737 MAX机型
So, soon after American’s order announcement, Boeing officially announced the 737 MAX.
该机型燃油效率比之前的737高15%
This aircraft would be 15% more fuel efficient than the previous 737 model
最大里程4400英里(7100公里)
and would therefore have a maximum range of 4,400 miles or 7,100 kilometers
相比之前737机型的3400英里(5400公里)
compared to the old 737’s 3,400 mile or 5,400 kilometer range.
这样一来，航司利用这款小型窄体飞机可以轻易跨大西洋飞行
This would make it easily possible to operate transatlantic flights on this small, narrow-body plane.
航司也的确有从这些长途、低需求航线中获利
Airlines did end up taking advantage of this range to operate long, yet low-demand routes.
比如，加拿大航空用737 MAX从哈利法克斯和圣约翰飞伦敦希斯罗
For example, Air Canada operated transatlantic flights from Halifax and St. John’s to London Heathrow using the 737 MAX.
挪威航空用其从纽约纽堡飞挪威卑尔根
Norwegian Airlines flew them as far as Newburgh, New York to Bergen, Norway.
同时，戈尔航空使用737 MAX每日从巴西的巴西利亚飞往佛州迈阿密
Gol Airlines, meanwhile, broke records with their daily 737 MAX flight all the way from Brasilia, Brazil to Miami, Florida
打破了八小时的飞行时间纪录
—an up to eight hour flight.
然而为了满足燃油效率和航程需求
To achieve the fuel efficiency and range improvement that made these flights possible, though,
波音必须对737做出几个关键改动
Boeing had to make a crucial change to the aircraft.
它们必须能够装更大的发动机
They had to fit bigger engines.
不说太多的工程上的东西
Without getting too much into the engineering,
最新、最高效的发动机体积都比之前的发动机大
the newest, most efficient engines are all physically larger than those of the past
因为设计上需要更多气流流经发动机的核心
due to designs that have more air bypass and flow past the engine core.
但问题是，737的设计让机身离地面太近了
The problem, though, was that the 737 design was quite low to the ground.
回到50年前，737刚刚设计出来的时候，小短腿设计其实很合理的
Back 50 years ago, when the aircraft was designed, this was a conscious choice.
该特性使其无需传送带就能装卸行李，无需升降机就能维护发动机
It was a feature that made it easy to load bags without a conveyor belt and maintain engines without a lift.
这让当时很多欠发达的机场简化了很多操作流程
This simplified operating to many of the less developed airports of that time.
这种小短腿设计对于737初代来说不是问题
This proximity to ground was no problem for the first generation of 737
因为当时发动机是像图中这样又细又长的
that had long and thin engines that looked like this.
对于第二代737——737经典
For the second generation, though, the 737 Classic,
波音将发动机进一步前移上移，进气口设计成非圆形来腾出空间
Boeing moved the engine further forward and up and designed its intake as non-circular to achieve more ground clearance.
下一代的737也沿用此设计，但到了MAX，就要装更大的发动机了
The next generation also kept this design, but then for the 737 MAX, they just had to fit an even larger engine.
所以，波音继续前移上移发动机，并提高前起落架8英寸(20厘米)
So, they put it even further forward and up in addition to adding 8 inches or 20 centimeters to the nose-gear.
然而这些改动改变了影响了飞机的气动，并影响了其操作
These changes, though, changed the aerodynamics of the plane and therefore how it handled.
使其比上一代更容易抬头，从而增加失速风险
It would cause the plane to pitch up more than the last generation which would put it at a greater risk of stalling.
所以波音安装了MCAS系统——机动特性增强系统
So, they installed a system called MCAS—the Maneuvering Characteristics Augmentation System.
该系统会在检测到飞机攻角过大时启动
This system would activate when it sensed the aircraft’s angle of attack was too high
并自动旋转水平尾翼来降下机鼻
and would automatically rotate the horizontal stabilizer to cause the aircraft’s nose to pitch down.
但飞机是通过一个传感器感知其攻角的
The aircraft figures out its angle of attack, though, through a sensor
如果传感器失效，会让飞机错误地认为自己攻角过大并自行改出
and if this sensor is broken, it can cause the aircraft to think it is flying at too high of an angle and self-correct.
此时若不关闭MCAS，飞机就会一直俯冲直至坠毁
Unless the system is deactivated, it can keep pitching the aircraft down until the ground.
人们相信这是2018年10月狮子航空610号班机失事的原因
It is this that is believed to have been the cause of the crash of Lion Air Flight 610 in October, 2018
也是2019年3月埃塞航302号班机失事的原因
and the crash of Ethiopian Airlines Flight 302 in March, 2019
它们也导致了如今737 MAX全球禁飞
and it is these that led to the grounding of every single 737 MAX in the world.
波音发现他们在2011年处于一种两难境地
Boeing found itself, back in 2011, in a position
易行的决策前景不好，前景好的决策执行会很艰难
where it had to choose between the easy wrong or the difficult right.
波音必须从短期和长期利益中取其一，而波音选择了前者
It had to choose between short-term and long-term gain and it chose to win now.
波音选择继续榨干一款古老机型
It chose to push the limits of an old design to a point
直到必须修改修改再修改还得保证仍然还是737
where it required correction upon correction to even make it the same plane.
但在2011年金融风暴的压力笼罩整个公司的时候
Given the storm of economic pressures surrounding the company in 2011, though,
波音的投资者肯定不愿意公司去花更多钱更多时间研发全新机型
Boeing’s investors would not have been happy if the company had embarked on a long, expensive new aircraft design process
而被空客的A320Neo抢占了市场先机
while Airbus engulfed market share with their A320Neo.
没人会想到当时在波音有惊人的安全记录的情况下
Nobody would have guessed at the time, with the company and aircraft’s phenomenal safety record,
这个决策会导致一款有缺陷飞机的诞生
that that decision would lead to a potentially faulty plane.
更没有人会想到这个决定会夺走346人的生命
Nobody would have guessed that the decision would potentially cost hundreds of lives.
这是由一些人拍脑袋作出的仓促决定
It was a hasty decision made by hasty human brains
波音及其737项目也会为此受到长期，甚至永久性的影响
and for that, Boeing and its 737 program will suffer long-term, possibly permanent consequences.
字幕翻译给虫，欢迎点赞投币收藏分享转发评论关注充电~
之后是恰饭时间
I’ve just re-done the Wendover Productions website with Wix which was a great, simple, and quick process.
One of the things I like about Wix is that they have a few different ways you can make your site
depending on your experience level and how much time you want to take.
You can have them make it for you using their artificial design intelligence,
you can make it yourself using the Wix editor, or for the experienced,
you can code your website easily with a bunch of extra features using their Corvid system.
Personally, I used the Wix editor and was able to quickly make a site that I think looks quite good.
Their designer templates and drag-and-drop website builder made it quite easy.
Wix’s paid plans are all quite reasonably priced and even include a custom domain name
but, you can start building your website today for free at wix.com/go/wendover.